A Guide to the Ellison A. Smyth, Sr. Papers, 1859-1927
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Ellison A. Smyth, Sr. Papers, 1859-1927
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1981-098
6.4 cu. ft. 8 boxes
The Ellison A. Smyth, Sr. collection contains papers including his correspondence with professional and amateur scientists, collectors, dealers and suppliers around the world concerning entomology and zoology, his publications, and field journals from his entomological work.
Smyth, Ellison A., Sr. (1863-1941)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Virginia Tech in multiple accessions from 1900 to 2011.
Biographical Note
Ellison Adger Smyth, Sr. was born in Summerton, South Carolina on October 26, 1863 and died in Salem, Virginia on August 19, 1941. Smyth received a Master's degree from Princeton in 1887 and an honorary degree of LL.D in 1906 from the University of Alabama. In 1891, Smyth moved to Blacksburg, Virginia in order to found the Biology Department at VPI with John McLaren McBryde. At VPI, Smyth was a Professor of Biology from 1891 until 1925, the first dean of the faculty from 1903-1906, the dean of the Department of Applied Science from 1916-1920, and faculty advisor to students in biology and pre-medical from 1920-1925. Ellison Adger Smyth, Sr. married Grace Allan in 1896, with whom he had five children.
Scope and Content
The Ellison A. Smyth, Sr. collection contains papers including correspondence with professional and amateur scientists, collectors, dealers and suppliers around the world, including H.H. Bailey, Carl Braun, Jonathan Dwight, E.K. Harvey, and James R. Randolph. The collection also includes correspondence with the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the American Entomological Society, Boston Society of Natural History, Linnean Society of New York, and the University of Notre Dame Botany Department; reprints of articles written by Smyth; literature on topics in biology and science; and his notes, written in 1912, on birds in Montgomery County, Virginia. Additionally, the collection contains a series of field journals and film negatives from Smyth's trips abroad. Other items in the collection include lecture notes (biology, botany, and evolution) and exam questions from the 1900s-1920s.
Please note: This collection does include Ellison A. Smyth, Sr.'s glass plate negatives. The glass plate negatives are not yet processed and are available upon request.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series, organized by material type.
Series I: Correspondence, includes personal and professional correspondence to and from Smyth. Loose letters are arranged alphabetically correspondent. Correspondence in letterbooks is in its original order. Series II: Elliot Society Ephemera includes information on the natural history organization, as well as publications from it. Series III: Publications and Research Notes contains copies of publications by Smyth and notes from his research in and around Montgomery County, Virginia. Series IV: Newspaper Clippings consists of a single scrapbook created by Smyth. Series V: Field Journals includes Smyth field research on a variety of biology and botany topics. Series VI: Teaching Materials consists of handwritten notes by Smyth during his tenure at Virginia Agriculture and Mechanical College. The majority of the notes relate to biology, botany, and evolution lectures, although there are also exam questions. Series VII: Photographic Negatives contains three collections of negatives--a set of images from Bedford County, Virginia; a set of images from Bermuda, taken in 1904; and a set of images taken in Jamaica in 1906.
Index Terms
Persons:
Smyth, Ellison A., Sr.
Subjects:
Faculty; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence A-P
    - American Educational Material (Box-folder 1-1)
    - American Entomological Society (Henry Skinner) (Box-folder 1-2)
    - American Museum of Natural History (Chapman) (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Audobon Society (Box-folder 1-4)
    - A (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Jas P. Babbitt (Box-folder 1-6)
    - H.H. Bailey (Museum of Natural History) (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Barrett (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Barrett's Latest (Box-folder 1-9)
    - P.B. Barringer (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Beutenmuller (American Museum of Natural History) (Box-folder 1-11)
    - H. Bodley (1904-1910) (Box-folder 1-12)
    - Carl Braun (Box-folder 1-13)
    - Brehme, H.H. (1898-1910) (Box-folder 1-14)
    - Burns, Fred (Box-folder 1-15)
    - HK. Burrison (M.I.T. 1894-1902) (Box-folder 1-16)
    - B (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-17)
    - The "Cabbage Snake" Scare (Box-folder 1-18)
    - Campbell, W.C. (Box-folder 1-19)
    - Caldwell, A.E. (Lizzie) (Box-folder 1-20)
    - Canada (Box-folder 1-21)
    - Carnegie (Box-folder 1-22)
    - Herbert R. Sass (Charleston Museum 1906-1912) (Box-folder 1-23)
    - Chicago Entomological Association (Box-folder 1-24)
    - B. Preston Clark (Box-folder 1-25)
    - Coker (Box-folder 1-26)
    - Columbia University (Box-folder 1-27)
    - Cormack, F. (Box-folder 1-28)
    - Cotton (Box-folder 1-29)
    - Crenshaw (Box-folder 1-30)
    - Victor M. Cushwa (Box-folder 1-31)
    - C (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-32)
    - John W. Daniel (Box-folder 1-33)
    - Walker Dannatt (Box-folder 1-34)
    - Denton (Box-folder 1-35)
    - G.M. Dodge (Box-folder 1-36)
    - Dr. Jonathan Dwight (Box-folder 1-37)
    - D (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-38)
    - J.D. Eggleston (Box-folder 1-39)
    - Elliot Society Proceedings (Box-folder 1-40)
    - Erb (Box-folder 1-41)
    - E (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-42)
    - Entomological Society of America (Box-folder 1-43)
    - Faculty (Box-folder 1-44)
    - Family (Box-folder 1-45)
    - William Field (Box-folder 1-46)
    - L.S. Foster (Box-folder 1-47)
    - Frazar (Box-folder 1-48)
    - French (Box-folder 1-49)
    - O. Fulda (Box-folder 1-50)
    - F (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-51)
    - Carter Class Letter (1908) (Box-folder 1-52)
    - G (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-53)
    - Leopold Hartman (Box-folder 1-54)
    - E.K. Harvey (Box-folder 1-55)
    - B.L. Hensel (Box-folder 1-56)
    - Howieson (Box-folder 1-57)
    - J.R. Hutcheson (Box-folder 1-58)
    - H (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-59)
    - I (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-60)
    - Johns (Box-folder 1-61)
    - J (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-62)
    - Keller (Box-folder 1-63)
    - Kny-Scheerer (Box-folder 1-64)
    - Kwiat (Box-folder 1-65)
    - K (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-66)
    - L (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-67)
    - J.M. McBryde (Box-folder 1-68)
    - McBryde, John M., Jr. (Box-folder 1-69)
    - The MacMillan Co. (Box-folder 1-70)
    - Markenhaus (Box-folder 1-71)
    - John H. Matthews (Importer) (Box-folder 1-72)
    - Mazyck (Box-folder 1-73)
    - A. Meik (Calcutta) (Box-folder 1-74)
    - Levi W. Mengel (Box-folder 1-75)
    - Frank A. & Harry D Merrick (Box-folder 1-76)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1-77)
    - M (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-78)
    - Newcomb (Box-folder 1-79)
    - Northwest Entomological Society (Box-folder 1-80)
    - D.O. Norse (Box-folder 1-81)
    - N (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-82)
    - Old Dominion Building & Loan (Box-folder 1-83)
    - Osgood (Box-folder 1-84)
    - Ottelengui (Box-folder 1-85)
    - E.T. Owen (Box-folder 1-86)
    - O (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 1-87)
    - R.W. Paul (Box-folder 1-88)
    - Personal/Business (Box-folder 1-89)
    - Personal (Box-folder 1-90)
    - Personal Cont. (Box-folder 1-91)
  - Correspondence P-Z
    - Personal/Family (Box-folder 2-1)
    - Personal/Recommendations (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Personal/Religion (Box-folder 2-3)
    - Personal/Income Tax (Box-folder 2-4)
    - Personal/Property Insurance/Stocks (Box-folder 2-5)
    - Professional A (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Professional B (Box-folder 2-7)
    - Personal/Professional (Box-folder 2-8)
    - Poe Shrine (Box-folder 2-9)
    - Pling Papers (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Porcher (Box-folder 2-11)
    - Princeton (Box-folder 2-12)
    - P (Box-folder 2-13)
    - Quaritch (Box-folder 2-14)
    - Q (Box-folder 2-15)
    - Rankine (Box-folder 2-16)
    - Wirt Robinson (Box-folder 2-17)
    - Wirt Robinson (Cont.) (Box-folder 2-18)
    - Rosenfeld (Box-folder 2-19)
    - R (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-20)
    - Salem (Box-folder 2-21)
    - Sawyer (Box-folder 2-22)
    - Scudder (Box-folder 2-23)
    - Seitz (Box-folder 2-24)
    - Shanks (Box-folder 2-25)
    - H. Skinner (Box-folder 2-26)
    - Smithsonian (Box-folder 2-27)
    - Smyth Family (Box-folder 2-28)
    - Souther (Box-folder 2-30)
    - Southern Planter (Box-folder 2-31)
    - Spencer Lens Co. (Box-folder 2-32)
    - Horatio S. Stahl (1908) (Box-folder 2-33)
    - Staudinger (Box-folder 2-34)
    - Stechert & Co. (Box-folder 2-35)
    - Stone (Box-folder 2-36)
    - H. Strecker (1893-1896) (Box-folder 2-37)
    - Swinhoe (Box-folder 2-38)
    - Claude A. Swanson (U.S. Senate) (Box-folder 2-39)
    - S (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-40)
    - Arthur H. Thomas Co. (Box-folder 2-41)
    - T (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-42)
    - USDA (Box-folder 2-43)
    - U (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-44)
    - VA Academy of Science (Box-folder 2-45)
    - VPI--Burruss (Box-folder 2-46)
    - VPI (I) (Box-folder 2-47)
    - VPI (II) (Box-folder 2-48)
    - VA State Museum (Box-folder 2-49)
    - VPI (Box-folder 2-50)
    - V (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-51)
    - W (Miscellaneous) (Box-folder 2-52)
    - R.J. Waith (Box-folder 2-53)
    - Arthur Wayne (Box-folder 2-54)
    - Frank B. Webster (Box-folder 2-55)
    - Werum Bros. (Box-folder 2-56)
    - William Wesley & Son (London 1901-1903) (Box-folder 2-57)
    - Woodrow Wilson, President (1917) (Box-folder 2-60)
    - Charles K. Worthen (Warsaw, Illinois) (Box-folder 2-61)
    - Wystman (Box-folder 2-62)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 2-66)
    - Y-Z (Box-folder 2-63)
    - Zoological Garden (Box-folder 2-64)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 2-65)
    - History VPI (Box-folder 2-66)
  - Letterbooks
    - Letters, 1896-1898 (Box-folder 6-6)
    - Letters, 1898-1900 (Box-folder 6-7)
    - Letters, 1900-1902 (Box-folder 6-8)
    - Letters, 1902-1905 (Box-folder 6-9)
    - Letters, 1904-1910 (Box-folder 6-10)
    - Letters, 1905-1906 (Box-folder 6-11)
    - Letters, 1906 (Box-folder 6-12)
- Series II: Elliot Society Ephemera
  - Proceedings of the Elliot Society of Natural History (1859) (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Journal of the Elliot Society of Natural History (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Rules for the Accentuation of Names in Natural History (Lewis B. Gibbes) (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Proceedings of the Elliot Society (1875-1889) (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Writings by Smith for the Experiment Station and Entomological News (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Reprints from Science Magazines (not written by Smyth) (Box-folder 3-7)
- Series III: Publications and Research Notes
  - Morpho Thoosa Smyth (1907) (Box-folder 4-1)
  - An Unusual Graafian Follicle. Reprinted from Biological Bulletin. (1908) (Box-folder 4-2)
  - "Poe's Gold Bug from the Standpoint of an Entomologist" (1910) (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Notes on Birds of Montgomery County, Virginia (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Birds Observed in Montgomery County, Virginia (Box-folder 4-5)
- Series IV: Newspaper Clippings
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 5-1)
- Series V: Field Journals
  - Catalogue of Lepidolptera Vol. I-III. (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Catalogue of Lepidolptera Vol. IV-V. (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Field Journals 1-4 (Box-folder 6-3)
  - Illustrations (Box-folder 6-4)
  - Pamphlets (Box-folder 6-5)
- Series VI: Teaching Materials
  - Biology Lectures and Notes (4 folders) (Box-folder 7-1 to 7-4)
  - Botany Lectures and Notes (3 folders) (Box-folder 7-5 to 7-7)
  - Botany Notes (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Evolution Lecture Notes (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Exam Questions (Box-folder 8-2)
- Series VII: Photographic Negatives
  - Bedford County, Virginia, Negatives (Box-folder 8-3)
  - Bermuda Negatives, 1904 (Box-folder 8-4)
  - Jamaica Negatives, 1906 (Box-folder 8-5)